<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>New World Epidemiology</title>
    <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project" />
    <updated>2019-12-14T15:11:03-08:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Pavan Tauh</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <author>
            <name>Pavan Tauh</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/abstract.html"/>
        <id>https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/abstract.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-13T20:23:00-08:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Background</title>
        <author>
            <name>Pavan Tauh</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/background.html"/>
        <id>https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/background.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-14T15:00:14-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/12/intro.jpg" alt="" />
                     Many misconceptions surround the Columbian Exchange—the “exchange of diseases, ideas, food crops, and populations between the New World and the Old World”—particularly those of an idyllic pre-Columbian disease-free New World and the Eurocentric “replacement theory” idea of a nonviolent and uncontested conquest of the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/12/intro.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>           Many misconceptions surround the Columbian Exchange—the “exchange of diseases, ideas, food crops, and populations between the New World and the Old World”—particularly those of an idyllic pre-Columbian disease-free New World and the Eurocentric “replacement theory” idea of a nonviolent and uncontested conquest of the New World.  With this project we aim to overturn some of those theories through their relationships to the spread of smallpox over time during the Columbian Exchange. We especially aim to use the lens of virgin soil epidemics and their impact on populations to prove that the colonization of the New World relied upon European violence against Native populations.</p>
<p>            A virgin soil epidemic is an outbreak of a disease that a population has never been exposed to—a well-known example of this is the smallpox virus’ effect on the New World.  Virgin soil epidemics were not unknown in the Old World—epidemics were unavoidable, especially with only a vague awareness of proper healthcare for victims of an epidemic. According to historian Suzanne Austin Alchon, all traditional medicinal systems share common factors including a dual curative/prophylactic purpose, a basis in drug therapy, and a search for the explanation of diseases’ causes.  These common responses in societies from Cuzco to Paris reveal the universal nature of societies’ reactions to virgin soil epidemics. However, in every other recorded case of a virgin soil epidemic, the native population remained a dominant power in their region. The sole exception our initial research turned up was the case of the Columbian Exchange, wherein European descendants now make up the majority of the population of the New World.  What made this outbreak so different?</p>
<p>            One hypothesis formulated by a number of Europeans visiting the New World under Spanish colonial rule was the “Black Legend,” a popular name for the ideas promulgated by Spanish priest Bartolomeo de las Casas.  The Black Legend essentially says that the brutality of Spanish colonial practices, especially against “small children, old men, pregnant women, and even women who had just given birth,” was the sole source of the collapse of Native civilizations in the New World (Alchon).  This rhetoric, while politically beneficial to Spain’s rivals and based mostly on observation (however exaggerated some of it may be), downplayed the role of diseases from the Old World in the conquest of the Americas. This theory is also related to a second error in historical thought: the common preconceived notion of an idyllic pre-Columbian disease-free world where every Native society lived peacefully, with no internal conflict nor existing epidemics.  As records show peoples in the Americas had their own manners of dealing with sickness, this is obviously not the case; it also feeds into a paternalistic attitude towards Native peoples in popular culture by treating Native Americans as a monolithic entity, as opposed to distinct cultural groups that often came into conflict with each other.</p>
<p>            In countering the exaggerations present in the formation of the Black Legend, some historians arrived at the conclusion that virgin soil epidemics such as smallpox were the overwhelming source of Native deaths from colonization, some going so far as to say that brutality on the part of the four major colonial powers (Spain, France, England, and Portugal) was negligible as disease was believed to have killed the majority of the population.  This flawed argument proved to have vast cultural ramifications in modern understandings of colonialism as well; it contributed to subconscious beliefs of white Americans being “original to place” in a phenomenon called the replacement narrative (Gilio-Whitaker). Modern historians’ hyperfixation on the diseases brought from the Old World to the New World led to a general ignorance of European violence against Native Americans, only contributing further to the narrative that Europeans arrived and simply replaced Native populations.  This obfuscates a long history of documented violence against Natives, as well as giving many Americans permission to ignore current patterns of environmental violence and physical violence on Native Americans.</p>
<p>              Our findings show that the replacement narrative has some small basis in truth, but that too great of a focus on the importance of disease in the Columbian Exchange leads to popular ignorance of the role European brutality played in the conquest of the Americas.  Evidence from multiple accounts confirms that non-Nahua visitors to Tenochtitlan, such as the Tarascan people, likely contracted smallpox from Europeans arriving in Tenochtitlan, and they then returned to outlying cities (Schwartz). The European colonizers would then arrive at these towns to find many dead and dying from disease, assuming that the epidemic could not have possibly come from the Europeans themselves.  While the replacement narrative may be loosely rooted in fact, it still ignores the fact that European violence was necessary to subjugate the Native populations of the Americas. Our expected data from future research will also hopefully negate the common paternalistic assumption that the New World was free of disease and conflict; we hope to map distinct pre-Columbian nations as well as the spread of syphilis, which we believe Christopher Columbus and his crew to have acquired in the West Indies and brought back to Europe, where it caused outbreaks in Spain.  Our current findings suggest that a combination of European colonial violence and the great impact of smallpox outbreaks were the reason that the Columbian Exchange was the sole major virgin soil epidemic to result in near-total population replacement.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Map of Diseases</title>
        <author>
            <name>Pavan Tauh</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/map.html"/>
        <id>https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/map.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-14T14:56:49-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                     In the end, we aimed to produce a map, and this was the hardest part of our project. The map above is an interactive map with points marking the recorded locations of smallpox during a particular outbreak, with the date viewable from each point.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><img class="post__image" src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/10/Map.jpg" alt="" width="1280" height="625"></p>
<p>          In the end, we aimed to produce a map, and this was the hardest part of our project. The map above is an interactive map with points marking the recorded locations of smallpox during a particular outbreak, with the date viewable from each point. While currently this website only contains a screenshot of the map, we will soon be integrating the actual code with the website so readers can interact with the information. We expected to do more with our map, but due to the complications of learning a new coding language and mapping tools, our first map took longer than we anticipated. As the project continues, we will add more elements to the map to better demonstrate and accentuate our findings. Our eventual map will demonstrate the spread of both syphilis and smallpox, with different overlays including a map of European colonies and one of Native American tribes, so we can place these dates and locations in context. The other significant feature we still haven’t added is the timeline progression within the map, so that we can view different rates of spread.</p>
<p>          The process for creating the map began first with data collection. Because there is almost no digital data on this subject, we had to search multiple books for information on the dates and locations of outbreaks. This took a significant amount of time, as we were manually collecting information. We still need to collect further information to add more evidence supporting our claims, which will be a continued process of reading historical texts.</p>
<p>          We took the data we found and placed it in an Excel spreadsheet and exported the data, using code that formatted the locations names and added their latitude and longitude. Then we took the formatted data, and placed it in a program called GeoJSON, which took the information in the spreadsheet and mapped it with the date located at each location point. This is the point at which the screenshot above was taken, with the map and GeoJSON code. This process took more work than expected, as the code originally written did not distinguish between East/West and North/South in the coordinates, so the first produced map originally mapped every point to India (ironically). With further adjustments, we managed to get each of the data points in the right location.</p>
<p>          Next, we will export this code as a GeoJSON file, and implement further Python code to set up an HTML web server to host our map. From there, we can then put the interactive map on the website, with the extra features mentioned previously. This process is difficult as the website is hosted on one account, while the map is hosted in a different location, so coordinating these and implementing them simultaneously will take further work.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Findings</title>
        <author>
            <name>Pavan Tauh</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/findings.html"/>
        <id>https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/findings.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-13T16:25:52-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/7/American-Indians-and-European-Diseases.jpg" alt="" />
                    Overall, we have found that disease spread faster than Europeans could travel. Just from their landing, Native Americans caught diseases and spread them to other tribes and cities. Due to this rapid spread, Europeans viewed the Native American populations as sicker and thinner than normal.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/7/American-Indians-and-European-Diseases.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Overall, we have found that disease spread faster than Europeans could travel. Just from their landing, Native Americans caught diseases and spread them to other tribes and cities. Due to this rapid spread, Europeans viewed the Native American populations as sicker and thinner than normal. </p>
<p>To address our original question, disease spread organically far more than by European force. Smallpox blankets and other forms of biological warfare may have hurt small groups of Natives during battle, but many Native Americans caught diseases before seeing a European. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Syphilis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Pavan Tauh</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/syphilis.html"/>
        <id>https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/syphilis.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-13T15:09:02-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/5/sy.jpg" alt="" />
                    Researchers debate the origin of syphilis, and usually agree with one of two theories. The first states that syphilis existed in Europe before Columbus returned, and that it was misdiagnosed as other diseases. The other theory states that it came from the Americas and spread&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://newworldepidemiology.github.io/Project/media/posts/5/sy.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Researchers debate the origin of syphilis, and usually agree with one of two theories. The first states that syphilis existed in Europe before Columbus returned, and that it was misdiagnosed as other diseases. The other theory states that it came from the Americas and spread along Europe only after Columbus returned. </p>
<p>From our data, the shape of a spread appears for syphilis reportings in Europe and Asia. This support the idea that European explorers brought the disease back with them, while before syphilis existed only in the New World.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
